Guide to the United Methodist Church Records, 1784-1984, bulk 1800-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- N.C. Conference Records Series, 1784-1974, bulk 1838-1939
  - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records Subseries, 1784-1974, bulk 1841-1919
    - Wake Co., 1850-1853, 1855-1944 and undated
      - Buckhorn Circuit, multiple districts, 1850-1853, 1855-1901, and undated (Box NCC55)
        1876: Circuit in Fayetteville District
        1881-1882: Circuit in Raleigh District
        1883-1884/1885: Circuit in Fayetteville District
        1885-1891: Circuit in Raleigh District
        1892-1901: Circuit in Fayetteville District
        Circuit includes Apex Church, Cokesbury Church, Buckhorn Church, Harnett Chapel, Olive Branch Church, Pleasant Plains Church, Ebenezer Church, and Holly Springs Church.
        - Buckhorn Church, Class Books, 1850-1853, 1855-1866, (3 volumes)
          Until 1858: Church in Haw River Circuit
        - Buckhorn and Cokesbury Churches, Subscription to support the gospel on Haw River and Buckhorn Circuits, 1855-1858
          Until 1858: Churches in Haw River Circuit
        - Church property petitions and reports, 1874-1900
        - Education reports, undated
        - Financial reports, 1876-1900
        - Membership and Sunday School lists, meeting minutes, and reports, 1857-1901 and undated, (2 folders)
        - Memorials of deceased ministers, 1884-1900 (Box NCC56)
        - Minister's reports to circuit quarterly conference, 1873-1895
        - Missionary contribution reports, 1897-1898, 1900-1901 and undated
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1871-1901, (2 folders)
        - Resolutions and Appointments, [ca. 1869] and undated
        - State of the Church reports to the circuit, 1871-1901 and undated
        - Steward meeting minutes, 1871-1901
      - Cary Circuit, Raleigh District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1912 (M-4292)
      - Franklinton Methodist Sunday School (MECS and MC), Records, 1901-1944
    - Warren Co., 1888-1894
      - [Henderson Station, Raleigh District, Treasurer's Book, 1888-1894 (F-6620): Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS4.] (Box NCC56)
      - [Roanoke Circuit, Warrenton District: See Halifax Co., Roanoke Circuit.]
    - Washington Co., 1887-1914
      - Washinton Station, Washington District, 1887-1914 (Box NCC56)
        - Church Conference Minutes, 1891-1911(M-2903)
        - Church Register, 1887-1893(M-2901)
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes
          - 1891-1894(M-2902)
          - 1911-1914(M-2904)
    - Unknown Co., 1887-1889
      - Zion Methodist Episcopal Sunday School, Librarian's Book, 1887-1889 (Box NCC56)
    - Unknown Co., Eastern N.C., 1911-1913
      - Bethany Church, Elizabeth City District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1912 (Box NCC56)
      - First Methodist Church, Washington District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1911-1913 (M-2898)
- Western N.C. Conference records Series, 1884-1962 and undated
  Comprises primarily bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes and church registers that document the administrative life of Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS) and Methodist Church (MC) circuits, charges, churches, missions, and stations in the western and west central counties of North Carolina. Counties include Alamance, Ashe, Burke, Catawba, Cleveland, Davidson, Forsyth, Iredell, Lincoln, Randolph, Rowan, and Yadkin, among others (1893-1932). The series also includes financial, administrative, and legal records for the Board of Missions and Church Extension of the Western N.C. Conference of the MECS (1909-1952) as well as quarterly conference and district conference minutes and trustees minutes for districts within the Western N.C. Conference including, among others, the Asheville and Winston-Salem districts (1912-1935). There is some overlap with the N.C. Conference. All records are MECS unless noted otherwise by the abbreviation MC for Methodist Church. Arranged in three subseries: Conference Records, District Records, and Circuit, Charge, and Church Records.
  - Conference Records Subseries, 1902-1952 and undated
    Comprises primarily accounting ledgers, financial records, executive committee meeting minutes, and correspondence (1909-1952) for the Board of Missions and Church Extension of the Western N.C. Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS) and the Methodist Church (MC). Also includes a Minute Book for the Board of Finance (1919-1939) and a journal of the annual conference (1902-1905). Arranged alphabetically. Oversize materials have been removed to the Oversize Materials section of this finding aid.
    - Board of Finance Minute Book, (MECS and MC), 1919-1939(L-2951) (Box WNC1)
    - Board of Missions and Church Extension
      - Accounting ledger, 1909-1938
      - Applications for aid (MECS and MC), 1912-1952, (1-6 of 19 folders)
      - Applications for aid (MECS and MC), 1912-1952, (7-17 of 19 folders) (Box WNC2)
      - Applications for aid (MECS and MC), 1912-1952, (18-19 of 19 folders) (Box WNC3)
      - Bank Book, 1915-1936
      - Bank statements and cancelled checks (MECS and MC), 1934-1951, (8 folders)
      - Executive Committee meeting minutes (MECS and MC), 1926-1942, (1-3 of 6 folders)
      - Executive Committee meeting minutes (MECS and MC), 1926-1942, (4-6 of 6 folders) (Box WNC4)
      - Letters (MECS and MC), 1927-1950 and undated, (1-9 of 30 folders)
      - Letters (MECS and MC), 1927-1950 and undated, (10-20 of 30 folders) (Box WNC5)
      - Letters (MECS and MC), 1927-1950 and undated, (21-30 of 30 folders) (Box WNC6)
      - Treasurer of the Conference (MC), 1938-1942
    - [Journal of the Western N.C. Conference, 1902-1905 (F-4289): Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS6.]
  - District Records Subseries, 1894-1935
    Comprises bound volumes of quarterly or district conference minutes and trustees minutes that document the administrative activities of districts within the Western N.C. Conference. There may be some overlap with the N.C. Conference. Districts with the largest number of records include Asheville (1912-1916) and Winston-Salem (1924-1935). Some districts were originally part of the either the Va. or S.C. Conferences, and this is noted next to their name.
    Arranged alphabetically by district name. Within most district names is included a list of counties represented in the district, as well as a list of the circuits, charges, and churches in this collection that were in that district. Names of districts represented in the Circuit, Charge, and Church Records Subseries but for which there no district-level records are also listed in this subseries. However, a list of counties and circuits, charges, and churches is not included for those districts for which the collection does not include circuit-level records. Date ranges in this series are given for district-level records only. Oversize materials have been removed to the Oversize Materials section of this finding aid.
    - Asheville District, 1912-1916 (Box WNC7)
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes
        - 1912-1913(M-5367)
        - 1913-1914(M-5368)
        - 1914-1915(M-5369)
        - 1915-1916(M-5370)
          Includes Shelby Station and Central Shelby, 1917-1920.
    - Charlotte District, 1913-1934 (See also the N.C. Conference.) (Box WNC7)
      - [District Conference Minutes and Trustees Minutes, 1913-1934 (F-4289): Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS7.]
    - Franklin District, 1910-1911 (Box WNC7)
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1910-1911
    - [Gastonia District: No district records] (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the Gastonia District: Lincoln.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Gastonia District: First Methodist Church/Station.
    - [Greensboro District: No district records. See also the N.C. Conference.] (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the Greensboro District: Alamance, and Randolph.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Greensboro District: Alamance Circuit; Randolph Circuit/Charge, and West Randolph Circuit.
    - [Lexington District: No district records] (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the Lexington District: Davidson, and Forsyth.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Lexington District: Lexington Circuit, and Winston Circuit.
    - [Lincolnton District: No district records. See also the N.C. Conference.] (Box WNC7)
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Lincolnton District: First Methodist Church/Station.
    - [North Wilkesboro District: No district records] (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the North Wilkesboro District: Ashe.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the North Wilkesboro District: Jefferson Circuit.
    - [Mount Airy District: No district records] (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the Mount Airy District: probably Yadkin.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Mount Airy District: West Davie Circuit.
    - [Salisbury District, Western N.C. and Va. Conferences: No district records. See also the N.C. Conference.] (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the Salisbury District: Rowan.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Salisbury District: Salisbury and Church Street Church.
    - [Shelby District, Western N.C. and S.C. Conferences: No district records. See also the N.C. Conference.] (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the Shelby District: Cleveland, and Lincoln.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Shelby District: Double Shoals and Polkville Circuits; First Methodist Church/Station; Polkville Church; Polkville Circuit; and Shelby Station and Central Shelby.
    - Statesville District, 1894 (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the Statesville District: Burke, Catawba, and Iredell.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Statesville District: Broad Street Church; Catawba Circuit; Iredell Charge; and Morganton Circuit.
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes of Presiding Elder, 1894(M-2977)
    - [Thomasville District: No district records] (Box WNC7)
      Counties represented in the Thomasville District: Catawba.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Thomasville District: Catawba Circuit; and Hopewell Church.
    - Winston-Salem District, 1924-1935 (Box WNC8)
      Counties represented in the Winston-Salem District: Forsyth.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Winston-Salem District: Winston Circuit.
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes
        - 1924-1925(M-5000)
        - 1925-1926(M-5001)
        - 1926-1927(M-5002)
        - 1927-1928(M-5003)
        - 1928-1929(M-5004)
        - 1934-1935
  - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records Subseries, 1884-1962,bulk 1893-1932
    Comprises primarily bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes and church registers that document the administrative life of Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS) and Methodist Church (MC) circuits, charges, churches, missions, and stations in the western and west central counties of North Carolina. There is some overlap with the N.C. Conference. Counties include Alamance, Ashe, Burke, Catawba, Cleveland, Davidson, Forsyth, Iredell, Lincoln, Randolph, Rowan, and Yadkin. Records that span a large number of years and comprise a complete set of minutes include Alamance Circuit (Alamance Co., 1893-1908), First Methodist Church/Station (Lincoln Co., 1902-1962), Jefferson Circuit (Ashe Co., 1893-1932), Morganton Circuit (Burke Co., 1889-1932), Polkville Circuit (Cleveland Co., 1911-1927), and Randolph Circuit/Charge (Randolph Co., 1893-1930). Although the majority of the records span the years 1893 to 1932, there are some records from 1884 (Hopewell Church, Catawba Circuit, Catawba Co.) and some records from the 1940s to the 1960s (First Methodist Church/Station, Lincoln Co.). In addition to the quarterly conference minutes and the church registers, there are also Sunday school records (Hopewell Church, Catawba Circuit, Catawba Co.) and a class book (Winston Circuit, Forsyth Co.).
    Arranged by county (boundaries current in 2004) and then alphabetically by circuit, charge, church, mission, or station name. Records from counties in the eastern and central sections of North Carolina can be found in the N.C. Conference Series. Additional information on circuits, charges, churches, missions, and stations may be found in the Western N.C. Conference Series, District Records Subseries, as well as the Historical Sketches Series, Circuits and Counties Subseries and the Churches and Cities Subseries. Information about ministers and other Methodists can be found alphabetically by last name in the Historical Sketches Series, Ministers Subseries, while overviews of Methodism in general, and in North Carolina and Virginia in specific, can be found in the Historical Sketches Series, Methodism Subseries. Oversize items have been removed to the Oversize Materials section of this finding aid. All circuit, charge, church, mission, and station names listed in this subseries can also be found alphabetically arranged without regard for their county, district, or conference location in the Circuit, Charge, and Station Index and the Church and Mission Index at the end of this finding aid. Baptismal records found in this collection can be located through the Baptismal Records Index.
    - Alamance Co., 1893-1908 (See also the N.C. Conference.)
      - Alamance Circuit, Greensboro District, 1893-1908 (Box WNC9)
        - Quarterly Conference Records/Minutes
          - 1893-1896(M-2957)
          - 1896-1900(M-2958)
          - 1900-1903(M-1959)
          - 1904-1908 (M-2960 and one folder)
    - Ashe Co., 1893-1905, 1908-1932
      - Jefferson Circuit, North Wilkesboro District, 1893-1905, 1908-1932 (Box WNC9)
        - Church Register
          - 1893-1905(F-2971)
          - 1908-1925(F-2972)
          - 1911-1929(F-2973) (Box WNC10)
          - 1921-1932(F-2974)
        - Quarterly Conference Record Book, 1926-1929(M-2975)
    - Burke Co., 1889-1902, 1906-1910, 1919-1924, 1928-1932
      - Morganton Circuit, Statesville and Marion Districts, 1889-1902, 1906-1910, 1919-1924, 1928-1932 (Box WNC10)
        Through 1932: Circuit in Statesville District
        At least 2004: Circuit in Marion District
        - Church Register, 1889-1902(F-2976)
        - Quarterly Conference Records
          - 1906-1910(M-2978)
          - 1919-1924(M-2979)
          - 1928-1932(M-2980)
    - Catawba Co., 1884-1895
      - Catawba Circuit, Statesville and Thomasville Districts, 1884-1895, 1955-1960 (Box WNC11)
        - Hopewell Church
          - General records (MC), 1955-1960
          - Sunday School Records, 1884-1895(M-2628)
    - Cleveland Co., 1892-1895, 1897-1920, 1923-1927 (See also the N.C. Conference.)
      - Double Shoals and Polkville Circuits, Shelby District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1892-1895(M-2953) (Box WNC11)
      - Polkville Church, Shelby District, Church Conference Record, 1897-1914 (M-2952)
      - Polkville Circuit, Shelby District, 1911-1927
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes
          - 1911-1914(M-2954)
          - 1915-1918(M-2955)
          - 1917-1927
          - 1923-1927(M-2956)
      - [Shelby Station and Central Shelby, probably Shelby District, 1917-1920: Found in the District Records Subseries, Asheville District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1915-1916.]
    - Davidson Co., 1898-1904
      - Lexington Circuit, Lexington District, Class Book, 1898-1904 (L-5923) (Box WNC11)
    - Forsyth Co., 1890-1907
      - Winston Circuit, Lexington and Winston-Salem Districts, 1890-1907 (Box WNC11)
        - Class Book, 1895-1901(L-5922)
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1890-1907(F-5921)
    - Iredell Co., 1894, 1917-1924
      - Broad Street Church, Statesville District, Church Register, 1917-1924 (Box WNC12)
      - Iredell Charge, Statesville District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1894
    - Lincoln Co., 1902-1962 (See also the N.C. Conference.)
      - First Methodist Church/Station, Lincolnton, Shelby and Gastonia Districts, 1902-1962 and undated (Box WNC12)
        Includes Lincolnton Station/Charge.
        - Church Register (MECS and MC), 1909-1954, (6 volumes)
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes/Records, 1902-1962, (1-2 of 11 volumes or folders)
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes/Records, 1902-1962, (3-10 of 11 volumes or folders) (Box WNC13)
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes/Records, 1902-1962, (11 of 11 volumes or folders) (Box WNC14)
      - [Lincolnton Station/Charge: Found in Lincoln Co., First Methodist Church/Station.]
    - Randolph Co., 1893-1896, 1901-1930 (See also the N.C. Conference.)
      - Randolph Circuit/Charge, Greensboro District, 1893-1896, 1901-1930 (Box WNC14)
        - [Church Register, 1902-1928 (F-2962): Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS6.]
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes
          - 1893-1896(M-2963)
          - 1901-1904(M-2964)
          - 1905-1908(M-2965)
          - 1909-1912(M-2966)
          - 1913-1915(M-2967)
          - 1919-1922(M-2968)
          - 1922-1925(M-2969)
          - 1927-1930(M-2970) (Box WNC15)
      - [West Randolph Circuit, Greensboro District, Circuit Register, 1902-1906: Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS6.] (F-2961)
    - Rowan Co., 1895-1898
      - Salisbury and Church Street Church, Salisbury District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1895-1898 (Box WNC15)
        1897: Church first listed as Church Street Church
    - Probably Yadkin Co., 1922-1923
      - West Davie Circuit, Mount Airy District, Quarterly Conference Records, 1922-1923 (M-5981) (Box WNC15)
- Historical Sketches Series, 1786-1997 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Comprises primarily historical and biographical information solicited from N.C. ministers about themselves, their churches, circuits, and counties in 1879 by H. T. Hudson and in 1895 by an unknown person. Also includes earlier and later additional additions, especially of typescript or handwritten articles, essays, or sermons on Methodism in N.C. Arranged into four subseries: Churches and Cities,Counties and Circuits, Methodism, and Ministers. For additional information, see also the Indexes to this collection.
  - Churches and Cities Subseries, 1887-1997 and undated
    Primarily handwritten answers by ministers to questions about their churches, solicited by an unknown person in 1895. Also includes other resource material compiled by local historians, church history committees, ministers, or other parishioners in the twentieth century, especially copies and/or transcriptions of land indentures, other legal documents, correspondence, photographs; lists of tombstones in church cemeteries; unpublished church histories; and newspaper clippings. Churches with the most information include Ebenezer United Methodist Church, Goldsboro, Wayne Co. (1980); Duke Memorial Methodist Episcopal Church, South, Durham, Durham Co. (1932, 1986); and Hopewell United Methodist Church, Burnsville, Anson Co. (1874, 1991). There is also some information about churches with mixed-race congregations, particularly Front Street Methodist Episcopal Church, South and Grace Church, both in Wilmington, N.C., and what happened to those congregations at the close of the Civil War.
    - Andrews Chapel UMC, Andrews-Soapstone Charge, Durham Co. (after 1927), 1979 (Box HS1)
    - Antioch UMC, Crouse, Gaston Co., Crouse and Pleasant Grove Charge, Gastonia District, W.N.C. Conference, 1968-1969
    - Asbury UMC, Durham, Durham Co., 1977
    - [Beston Church, Wayne Co., LaGrange Ct., New Bern Dist., undated: Found in Piney Grove Church.]
    - [Bethany Church, probably Craven Co., undated: Found in Dover Old Church.]
    - [Bethany Church, undated: Found in Grace Church, Morganton.]
    - Bethany Church, Wilmington, probably New Hanover Co., 1895
    - [Bethel Church, Wayne Co., LaGrange Ct., New Bern Dist., undated: Found in Piney Grove Church.]
    - Bethel Church, Brunswick Co., Brunswick Ct., Wilmington Dist., 1895
    - Bethlehem UMC, Sydnorsville, VA, Franklin Co., South Franklin Ct., 1989, 1995
    - Bladen Street Church, probably Wilmington, 1895
    - Browning's Chapel, Sampson Co., 1895
    - [Carr Church, Durham, Durham Co., 1895: Found in Trinity Church, Durham.]
    - Clinton Church, Clinton, Sampson Co., Clinton Ct., 1895
    - Council Methodist Church, Bladen Co., Carvers Creek Ct., Wilmington Dist., 1997
    - Dover Old Church, undated
      Includes Epworth Church and Bethany Church.
    - Duke's Chapel MECS, Durham, Durham Co., 1927
    - Duke Memorial MECS, Durham, Durham Co., Durham Dist., 1932, 1986, (2 folders)
    - Ebenezer United Methodist Church, Goldsboro, Wayne Co., approximately 1980
    - Edwards Chapel, Edwards, probably Pitt Co., LaGrange Ct.
    - [Epworth Church, probably Craven Co., undated: Found in Dover Old Church.]
    - Fifth Street Station, probably Wilmington, Wilmington Dist. (after 1850), 1895 (See also Front Street Church.)
    - Franklinton United MC, Franklinton, Franklinton Ct., 1989
    - Front Street MC, Wilmington, 1865 (See also Fifth Street Station.), (2 folders)
      Includes drafts and research for Lingurn Skidmore Burkhead's History of the Difficulties of the Pastorate of the Front Street Methodist Church..., published 1908-1909.
    - Goshen Church, probably Clinton, Sampson Co., Clinton Ct., 1895
    - Grace Church, Morganton, probably 1895
      Includes Bethany Church.
    - Grace Church, Wilmington, 1895
    - Gray's Chapel MPC, probably Franklinville, Randolph Co., probably Alamance Ct., 1996
    - Grifton ME Church, Grifton, Grifton Ct., 1895
    - Gum Swamp Church, probably Pitt Co., probably Grifton Ct., 1895
    - Hookerton Church, probably Snow Hill Ct., 1895
    - Hopewell UMC, Burnsville, Anson Co., W.N.C. Conference, probably Polkton and Peachland Cts., 1984, 1991
    - Johnson's Chapel, probably Clinton, Sampson Co., probably Clinton Ct., 1895
    - Keener's Chapel, probably Clinton, Sampson Co., probably Clinton Ct., 1895
    - Kendall's Chapel, probably Clinton, Sampson Co., probably Clnton Ct., 1895
    - Lakewood MC, Durham, Durham Co., 1962
    - Lane's Chapel MC, probably Dover, probably Craven Co., Craven Ct., 1961
    - Lang's MC, Pitt Co., probably Farmville Ct., probably Washington Dist., 1970
      Includes copy of a deed, 1894.
    - Lexington Church, probably 1879
    - Macedonia Church, near Southport, probably Brunswick Co., probably Brunswick Ct., probably Wilmington Dist., 1895
    - [Main Street Church, Durham, Durham Co., 1887: Found in Trinity Church, Durham.]
    - Mann's Chapel, Chapel Hill, Chatham Co., circa 1985
    - Market Street ME Church, Wilmington, probably Market St. Ct., probably 1895
    - Mount Hebron MECS, Durham, Durham Co., undated
    - Mt. Olivet Church, probably Montgomery Co., probably 1879
    - Mt. Pleasant Church, Clemmons, Forsyth Co., Stokes Dist., 1973-1974, 1960
    - New Hope Church, near Southport, Brunswick Co., Brunswick Ct., Wilmington Dist., 1895
    - Newport Church, undated
    - Onslow Mission, probably 1895
    - Piney Grove Church, Wayne Co., probably LaGrange Ct., probably New Bern Dist.
      Includes Beston Church and Bethel Church.
    - Pleasant Green Church, list of graves in churchyard, probably Orange Co., 1981 (Box HS2)
    - Pleasant Union UMC, probably Randolph Co., undated
      Was Methodist Protestant.
    - Providence UMC, Wayne Co., Falling Creek-Providence Charge, circa 1988
    - Rainbow Church, Green Co., New Bern Dist., Hookerton Ct., 1936
    - Rehobeth UMC, cemetery history and census, probably Guilford Co., circa 1978